Guide to the Orator F. Cook Papers 1889-1898
University of Chicago Library
Cook, Orator F. Papers
1889-1898
3.5 linear ft. (7 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Orator F. Cook, botanist. The Orator F. Cook Papers consist of materials pertaining to Cook's activities in Liberia from 1889 to 1898 including correspondence, clippings, business records and photographs. The collection also includes biographical materials about Cook.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Digital Images
Original documents, texts, and images represented by digital images linked to this finding aid are subject to U. S. copyright law. It is the user's sole responsibility to secure any necessary copyright permission to reproduce or publish documents, texts, and images from any holders of rights in the original materials.
The University of Chicago Library, in its capacity as owner of the physical property represented by the digital images linked to this finding aid, encourages the use of these materials for educational and scholarly purposes. Any reproduction or publication from these digital images requires that the following credit line be included: Special Collections Research Center, University of Chicago Library.
Commercial publication projects require the permission of the University of Chicago Library and may be subject to a use fee. To order publication-quality reproductions, or for permission to copy or use any part of the digital images attached to this finding aid for any commercial purposes, please contact the Special Collections Research Center.
The images presented here may include materials reflecting the attitudes, language, and stereotypes of an earlier time period. These materials are presented as historical resources in support of study and research. Inclusion of such materials does not constitute an endorsement of their content by the University of Chicago.
The University of Chicago Library appreciates hearing from anyone who may have information about any of the images in this collection.
Biographical Note
Orator F. Cook was an American botanist who specialized in cotton and rubber plants, as well as in the classification of palms. Born in 1867 in Clyde, New York, Cook graduated from Syracuse University in 1890, where he stayed on as an instructor for one year. He traveled extensively in many parts of the world collecting botanical specimens, and from 1891 to 1898 he was employed as a special agent of the New York State Colonization Society. He spent much of his time in Liberia, and in 1896, Cook was elected president of Liberia College, a position, which he held until 1898. From 1898 he served as a plant scientist with the U. S. Department of Agriculture, where he became Principal Botanist. He published almost four hundred books and articles during his life, and was awarded an honorary Doctorate of Science by Syracuse University in 1930.
Scope Note
The collection has been divided into six series. Series I, General Correspondence includes exchanges related to Cook's work in Liberia and with his scientific colleagues. Series II, Personal Correspondence, primarily contains letters between Cook and Alice Carter, who he married in 1892. Series III contains documents related to Liberia, as does Series VI (oversize materials.) Series IV includes photographs of Liberia and the Canary Islands. Series V is a biographical calendar of Cook's life, prepared by his daughter Helen Newman.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Cook, O. F. (Orator Fuller). 1867-1949; Canary Islands; Liberia; Botanists; Photographs.
INVENTORY
- Series I: General Correspondence
  These letters are organized alphabetically, and include correspondence from J. Braman of the Trustees of Donations for Education in Liberia, Charles Geyer of the New York Colonization Society, and Reverend George Goll of the Board of Foreign Missions, as well as letters from colleagues who participated in his survey of Mount Coffee, Liberia, such as botanists Guy Collins and Fred Straub. There is extensive correspondence with Lucien M. Underwood, Cook's teacher at Syracuse University.
  - Allen - Agassiz (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barclay - Buchanan (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cheeseman - Coleman (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Collins, Guy (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cook - Currie (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Daly - Ennis (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fair - Frisell (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Geyer, Charles (New York State Colonization Society) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gibson - Goll (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Goode - Goche (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hartzell - Hookway (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Houghton (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Houghton - Locke (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - McCabe - Merrill (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Merrick - Morgan (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - New York Age - Osborne (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Page - Public Opinion Company (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Richardson - Sevier (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sharp (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sharp - Stewart (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Straub, Fred (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Straub, cont. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Straub, cont. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Taylor - Thompson (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Trio Club - True (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Underwood, Lucien (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Underwood, cont. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Underwood, cont. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Underwood - Verdoorn (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Walrath - Wood (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series II: Personal Correspondence
  This series primarily consists of correspondence between Orator Cook and Alice Carter, who he married in 1892. These letters highlight their private interests and concerns, but also contain information pertaining to Cook's whereabouts during his travels and his general plans. Miscellaneous letters from other family members also appear in this series, as well as some of Alice's letters to friends at Mount Holyoke College where she taught botany.
  - Family correspondence of Alice Carter Cook (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence of Alice and Orator Cook with Edith and Eliza Cook (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, October 1888 - August 1891 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, September 1892 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, October 1891 - November 1891 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, December 1891 - May 1892 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, June 1892 - September 1892 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, December 1893 - January 1894 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, February 1894 - April 1894 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, May 1894 - December 1895 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, July 1896 - August 1897 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Alice Carter to Orator Cook, October 1897 - November 1897 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, June 1891 - July 1891 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, August 1891 - September 1891 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, October 1891 - December 1891 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, January 1892 - June 1892 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, July 1892 - October 1892 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, April 1893 - March 1894 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, March 1894 - November 1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, December 1895 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, January 1896 - July 1896 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Orator Cook to Alice Carter, November 1896 - November 1897 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series III: Liberian Documents
  These documents include articles and clippings on Liberia, information on Liberian folklore, articles on botany, and miscellaneous business material.
  - Liberia (magazine of the American Colonization Society), February 1898 and November 1898, including articles by Cook; clippings on colonization (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Charter, Constitution, By laws and Financial Report of the New York Colonization Society, 1891; Third Report of the Board of Managers of the New York Colonization Society, New York: 1896; Report of O. F. Cook to the Board of Managers, New York: 1892 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - African Planter, 1894-1895 (incomplete run) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings and pamphlets on lynching and racial conflicts in the United States, 1890s-1900s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings and pamphlets on lynching and racial conflicts in the United States, cont. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Clippings and articles on Liberia (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Drafts of official documents related to Liberian interests, 1890s; typescript drafts of articles on colonization by Cook; typescript "Report upon Collections made in Liberia, West Africa, February to March 1897," by Rolla P. Currie (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Liberian folklore (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lucien M. Underwood and other authors, off-prints dealing with botanical subjects, 1890s-1900s (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Guy Collins, obituary (off-print, with original photograph attached); remarks by the Secretary of Agriculture for the presentation of the Meyer Medal to "David Fairchild, Plant Explorer," 1939 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Programs (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Invoice statements relating to research and expedition supplies, 1891-1892 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Invoice statements relating to research and expedition supplies, 1893-1894 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Invoice statements relating to research and expedition supplies, 1895-1896 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Orator Cook's personal account book and general log, regarding work for the New York State Colonization Society and others (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous documents related to international trade (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Photographs
  These are black and white photographs of the people and landscape of Liberia and the Canary Islands, 1890s-1900s, in various formats. Some of the photographs are identified on the verso.
  - Canary Islands (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Canary Islands (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Liberia (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Liberia (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Liberia, views of "The Farm" (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Series V: Biographical Materials
  These documents are a general biographical calendar. This calendar description of Cook's life spans 1891-1897. It was prepared by his daughter, Helen Newman.
  - Biographical calendar of Cook's life, March 1891-December 1892 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Biographical calendar of Cook's life, January 1893-1897 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Orator Cook and Guy Collins, Economic Plants of Porto [sic] Rico, Washington, DC, Smithsonian Institution, 1903, 269 p. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Pamphlets bound together into one volume, Act Incorporating Liberia College, Monrovia, 1864 The Laws of Liberia College, Cambridge, 1883 Thirty-Second Annual Report of the Board of Managers of the New York State Colonization Society, New York, 1864 Charter, Constitution and By-Laws of the New York State Colonization Society, New York, 1891 A Statement of the Condition of Liberia College, Monrovia, 1894 Acts Passed by the Legislature of the Republic of Liberia, Monrovia, 1894 Report of the Dr. Charles E. Thomson and Prof. Guy N. Collins to the Board of Managers of the New York State Colonization Society, 1892 Reports of Prof. O.F. Cook to the Board of Managers..., New York, 1892 Second Report of Prof. O.F. Cook to the Board of Managers..., New York, 1894; with notes, tipped in, and holograph annotations (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series VI: Oversize Materials
  This series primarily holds newspapers and other printed material from Liberia.
  - Liberia Gazette, 1894-1985 (incomplete run) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lagos Weekly Record, 1894-1895 (incomplete run) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Publications, Voice of Missions (Atlanta, George) March 1897 The colored American (Washington, D.C.) August 20, 1898 The New York Age, December 19, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Orator Cook, Memorial to the People and Government of Liberia, January 17, 1896 (2 copies) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Afrikanische Dampfschiffs-Actien-Gesellschaft, Woermann-Linnie (shipping passenger boat time-table, Hamburg to West Africa route), July to September 1894; and Woermann-Linie, 1896, both schedule annotated with the names of the captains (Box 7, Folder 5)